ROBERT MCCRATE PAPERS (APAP026) 1959-1962
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
Robert McCrate Papers1956-1962
nam_apap026
MacCrate, Robert
5.0 processed to date
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, SUNY
Robert MacCrate is a lawyer who have served at the pleasure of NY State as a counsel.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Robert MacCrate, on July 7, 1989.
Scope and Content Information
This manuscript collection contains retained copies of memoranda (1959-62) sent to Governor Rockefeller by his counsel, Robert MacCrate, concerning pending bills in the New York Senate and Assembly. Bound with the memoranda are copies of the Governor's approval or veto messages for the bills. The memoranda and approval or veto messages are arranged by year and source of the bill (Senate or Assembly), and thereunder by bill number. All bills considered by the legislature are not included in this collection, but the range of subjects in the bills that were considered by MacCrate was quite large including business regulations, court reorganization, education law and zoning regulations. Yearly subject indexes to the Governor's approval and veto messages for both Assembly and Senate bills appear at the end of the last volume for each year.
Administrative History
Robert MacCrate was born in Brooklyn, N.Y., on July 18, 1921. He married Constance Trapp on May 4, 1946, and they had three children: Christopher Robert, Barbara Constance, and Thomas John. MacCrate received a B.A. from Haverford College in 1943, and an LL.B. from Harvard University in 1948. He was accepted to the New York bar in 1949 and to the District of Columbia bar in 1965. He was an associate of the firm Sullivan and Cromwell in New York city from 1948 to 1955, and later he was a partner (1956-59, 1962-present). He was law secretary to New York Appelate Division Presiding Justice David W. Peck (1951), and counsel to New York Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller (1959-62). Under Governor Rockefeller, MacCrate, served as associate counsel (Feb. 2, 1959-June 1, 1959) and then counsel (June 1, 1959-June 30, 1962). The primary responsibility of counsel to the governor was to translate the governor's programs into law. He and his staff ensured that bills were correctly drafted and helped to prevent enactment of bills that were antithetical to the governor's programs. Along with the budget director and the secretary to the governor, the counsel was one of the people on whom Governor Rockefeller relied most heavily for administration and program development. Macratae later serves as special counsel to the U.S. Army investigation into the Mylai incident (1969-70), counsel of the New York State Court on Judiciary (1971), and President of the American Bar Association (1987-89). He has contributed articles to professional journals.[1]
Arrangement of the Collection
Box and Folder List
Subject and Genre Headings
Public Servants; MacCrate, Robert; Legislature; New York (State)--Social Conditions; Legislature
Container List
- Assembly Bills, 1-2999, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Assembly Bills, 3000-end, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Senate Bills, 1-2499, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Senate Bills, 2500-end, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Assembly Bills, 1-2999, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Assembly Bills, 3000-end, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Senate Bills, 1-2999, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Senate Bills, 3000-end, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Assembly Bills, 1-2999, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Assembly Bills, 3000-end, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Senate Bills,1-2499, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Senate Bills, 2500-end, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Assembly Bills,1-3299, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Assembly Bills, 3300-end, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Senate Bills, 1-2699, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Senate Bills, 2700-end, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 3)